A Guide to the Peter K. Olitsky papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA184
Rockefeller Archive Center
Peter K. Olitsky papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1925-1964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Olitsky, Peter K.
FA184
3 Cubic Feet 4 boxes, 7 volumes
Biographical/Historical note
Peter Kosciusko Olitsky, 1886-1964, pathologist and microbiologist at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1917-1964. An outstanding virologist and investigator of epidemic diseases of bacterial, viral and rickettsial nature.
Biographical note
1886 Born August 20, New York, New York
1909 M.D. Cornell University, New York
1909-1911 Internship (Hospital later absorbed by St. Marks Hospital)
1911-1912 Private practice of medicine
1912-1913 New York City Health Department Research Laboratory
1913-1916 Eugene Meyer Fellowship in Pathology, Pathology Laboratory, Mt. Sinai Hospital, New York
1917 Assistant, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York, N.Y.
1918 Associate, RIMR
1923 Associate member, RIMR
1930 Member, RIMR
1952- Emeritus Member, RIMR
1956 Closed laboratory Worked as consultant and advisor with Howard Schneider on experimental allergic encephalomyelitis (EAE)
1964 Died July 20, Greenwich Hospital, Greenwich, Conn.
Served on:
1918-1919 1st Lt. USA Medical Corps
1925-1927 U.S. Bureau of Animal Industry
1930- Consultant in pathology, Greenwich Hospital
1941-1945 U.S. Army Commission on Neurotropic Virus Diseases
1952 WHO/FAO Panel on zoonoses, United Nations, Geneva Associate Editor, Journal of Immunology
Member of: New York Academy of Medicine (Fellow), American Association of Immunologists, Harvey society, Society for Exp. Biology and Medicine, Sigma Xi
Scope and Contents note
Papers, correspondence, photographs, reprints, and employment record.
Arrangement note
Arranged by subject and chronological.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 OL4
Related Archival Materials note
A collection of Peter K. Olitsky Papers, consisting of 2500 pieces is to be found at The American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Rickettsia; Bacteria; Viruses -- Research; Diagnostic virology; Microbiology; Epidemics; Epidemiology; Medical research; Pathology; Life sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biochemistry; Diseases; Biology -- Research; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Olitsky, Peter K.
- Biographical material; bibliography, 1948 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes statement on his work written in 1948 at the request of H.S. Gasser.
- Correspondence regarding presentation to RIMR of portrait of PKO at his retirement from his associates, 1953 (Box 1)
  Includes holograph drafts of letters of thanks.
- Correspondence dealing with arrangements at closing of laboratory (Box 1)
- Reprint of S. Gard 1954 Nobel Prize presentation quoting Olitsky work on neurotropic virus (Box 1)
- Reprint of Report of the Foot-and-Mouth-Disease Commission of the U.S. Department of Agriculture (Box 1)
- Photographs (Box 1)
  Primarily of co-workers. Some of PKO. Anslow, R.; Boes; Canti, R.G.; Casals, J.; Cox, H.R.; Forsbock, F.C.; Harford; Gates, F.L.; Kligler; Knutti; Larsen, S.; Lee J.M.; Muller, L.; Long; Morgan; Plotz, H.; Saenz; Straub, E.L.; Syverton, J.; Tal (Max child); Theiler, Max; Yager; Welch, W.H.
- Fishing trip: Parker, Cox, Kaa, Humble, Olitsky, 1936 (Box 1)
- Strasbourg: Traum, Schoening, Boez, 1926 (Box 1)
- Harold Olden (nephew) (Box 1)
- Strasbourg; Hong Kong; RIMR; Hoof and Mouth Disease (Box 1)
- Passports and visas (Box 1)
  Includes delayed birth registration.
- Framed pencil drawing made by stepdaughter, Louise Tubby Bracken about 1956. Given by W. Goebel (Box 1)
- Oral history (1917-1952) transcript. Interviews by Saul Benison, 1962-63. 91 pp. Indexed, 1917-1952, 1962-1963; 91 pp. (Box 1)
- Personal correspondence, 1946-1963 (Box 1)
  Includes birthday greetings from wife [n.d.]; August 1946 letters from associates on 60th birthday. Letters dealing with health of various family members including daughter, Ruth, and stepson Roger Tubby; a few family letters from nephew H. Sparrow, Louise Sparrow, B. Carpenter and granddaughter, Susue; letters regarding estate of Louis Olden. Thank you letter from daughter Louise Phillips and correspondence with stepson Roger Tubby. Copies of poems composed by PKO on various laboratory occasions.
- Obituary materials collected on various associates by PKO for use in his own writing, 1888-1930 1950 1952 1954-1960 (Box 1)
  Includes material on P. Boez, 1888-1930; on Simon Flexner including biographical article written for Collier's Encyclopedia with 1960 correspondence; biographical article on Frederick L. Gates and 1950, 1952, 1954 correspondence with Dorothy Elsmith, widow of F.L. Gates, and also with daughter.
- Administrative correspondence, 1921, 1942-1963; 2 items dated 1921 (Box 2)
  Primarily official announcements though includes renewals of allowances for supplies and some specialized items.
- Assorted correspondence, 1944-1963; 4 folders (Box 2)
  Correspondents include: C.H. Andrewes; C.H. Archetti; Alberto Ascoli; Gilbert Dalldorf; Brig. Gen. G.M. Findlay; Jordi Folch; Jules Freund; Chas. L. Goldman; Joan Fitzgerald Golrick; A. Grumback; Frank L. Horsfall; Martin M. Kaplan; Hilary Koprowski; C.L. Le Bouvier; Henryk Makower; A. Saenz; Kenneth C. Smithburn; Isabel Morgan Mountain; Maria Rudzinska; Madge Stein; Maurizio Terni; Rudolph Wittkower; Ralph W.G. Wyckoff.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1944-1951
    Scope and Contents
    Items of special interest are listed below this level.
    - With John R. Paul and Brig. Gen. S. Bayne-Jones on publication of "Certain affections of the liver that arise spontaneously in so-called Normal stock albino mice." Under Commission on Neurotropic Virus Diseases, 1945 July 11-November 1
    - With John R. Paul on publication of "Enduring Immunity following vaccination of mice with Formalin-inactivated virus of Russian Spring-Summer (Far Eastern, Tick borne) encephalitis..." Under Commission on Neurotropic Virus Diseases, 1945 September 12-1945 November 9
    - 1948 September 14
    - 1949 January 25
    - With David Bodian on "MV" strain of polio virus and monkey immune serum, 1950 September-October
    - With Harold K. Faber and A. Sabin work on mechanism of infection in post tonsillectomy bulbar polio, 1951 August 6-10
  - 1952-1954
    - On dinner in honor of J. Bronfenbrenner, 1952 March 21
    - With J. Folch-Pi on Waksman (et al) abstract in Fed. Proc. no. 1526, 1953 March 17-24
  - 1955-1959
    - Copy of letter from A.B. Sabin to Hilary Koprowski with holograph note to PKO, 1955 March 31
    - From M.S. Shahan on retirement of Jacob Traum, 1956 March 30
    - With Jules Freund (holographs) on diagnosis of multiple myeloma and his state of health, 1957 November 18-21
    - With George W. Corner on history of RI, 1958 January-December
    - With John H. Dingle on statement regarding etiology of the common cold. Olitsky refers to work of A.B. Sabin, 1958 October-November
  - 1960-1963
    - With A.A. Hoehling requesting that PKO write an introduction to book for laymen on 1918 influenza epidemic, 1959 November-1960 October
      Includes holograph note from James P. Leake, and history note from PKO to E. Kone.
    - From Philip Levine on difficulties in writing an address on Karl Landsteiner, 1960 June 21
    - To George S. Mirick recommending Labe C. Scheinberg for Health Research Council Fellowship, 1962 January 8
- Correspondence
  Arranged in alphabetical order where there are more than 25 items for each correspondent. Chronological within folder.
  - Anslow, Ralph, 1950-1963 (Box 2)
    Related Materials
    See also Joan Fitzgerald Golrick's letters from Washington, D.C. describing the work going on in the Army Medical Veterinary Division with Major Anslow.
  - Avery, Julian, 1947-1949 1958 (Box 2)
    An involved group of letters dealing with interest in a theory of fundamental particles proposed by Mr. Avery and attempts by PKO to aid in its publication.
    Includes copies of letters from John A. Wheeler, Princeton University; A. Einstein; George A. Baitsell; Alexandre Rothen.
  - Bernkoff, Hans, 1946-1950 (Box 3)
  - Brown, Lenora (Irwin/Simnad), 1951-1958 (Box 3)
    Some holograph letters and reports from Dr. Brown and one signed typescript from Jonas Salk.
  - Casals, Jordi, 1944-1951 (Box 3)
    Several holograph letters; 2 from Japan while at 406th Medical General Laboratory.
  - Cox, Herald R., 1952-1960; some holograph letters (Box 3)
  - Dick, George W.A., 1948-1955; some holographs (Box 3)
  - Flexner, Abraham, 1920 1937 1951 (Box 3)
    Includes two Simon Flexner reprints: 1920, 1937. On mementos and correspondence relating to S. Flexner.
  - Flexner, Simon, 1925-1926 (Box 3)
    Copies of letters written from Strasbourg on Hoof and Mouth Disease Project.
  - Lee, Johanna M., 1952-1961 (Box 3)
    Many holograph letters written during times of illness. Letters reporting experimental results while PKO away from laboratory.
  - Schlesinger, R. Walter, 1946-1963 (Box 3)
    Includes letter to PKO (1963 Apr. 30) explaining background to T. River's remarks to Saul Benison about A. Sabin's attitude on Schlesinger's work on dengue and sandfly fevers.
  - Selzer, Golda, 1952-1959 (Box 3)
  - Smadel, Joseph E., 1946-1950 (Box 3)
    Contains references to H. Bernkoff, Col. Yager.
  - Syverton, Jerome T., 1955-1961 (Box 3)
  - Tal, Chloe, 1954-1961 (Box 3)
    Includes reprint from British Journal of Experimental Pathology, 2 April. 1958.
- Subject folders (Box 3)
  - W.E.E. vaccine, 1942-1943
    Includes 1942 July 15 signed letter from Albert Sabin and copy of 1942 Nov. 24 letter from A. Sabin on efficacy of allantoic fluid vaccine and potency when stored.
  - Diseases of Poultry (Iowa State Press), 1947-1957
    Chap. 23: Avian encephalomyelitis by Henry van Roekel and Chap. 27: Foot and Mouth Disease by Harry Schoening including holograph letter 7 Jan. 1957 on his retirement and request to pass on to Dr. Shahan the authorship of the chapter.
  - Brennemann's Practice of Pediatrics, 1942-1962
    1942 and later revisions of Section II: "Infections of man with the virus of equine encephalomyelitis".
  - Viral and Rickettsial Infection in Man, 1951-1959
    Copies of Chap. 13 and 14, 3rd ed. mss. 1951-1959.
    Includes correspondence with Frank Horsfall and others.
    Includes some correspondence on 2nd. ed. under editorship of T. Rivers 1951-1952 including letters from A. Sabin, 22 May 1951; K. Smithburn 19 Mar. 1951; J. Melnick 22 Mar. 1951; Joe Smadel, holograph 12 April 1951.
- Correspondence and employment record, 1925-1964; 1 box (2½ inches)
  Consists primarily of the correspondence with directors and business managers during the period of Dr. Olitsky's association with The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research.
  Included is the original application for employment and many handwritten letters from Dr. Olitsky in response to increased salary letters.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Received or inventoried June, 1980. This box (5 folders) of papers was deposited by the Office of Faculty and Student Records.
  Arranged by subject and in chronological order.
  - Correspondence, 1912-1934 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and blueprints for remodeling and air duct arrangement in Olitsky laboratory, 1931-1933 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from the lay public with various ideas about polio which Peter Olitsky answered, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Signed releases for those vaccinated and working in the Olitsky laboratory with equine encephalitis virus, 1941-1947 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Influenza Reprints, 1920-1924; 1 volume
- Collected Reprints, 1915-1945; 6 volumes
- Lantern slides, 1982 September 15; oversize package #1 (Package 1)
  Wm Trager to RUA (9/15/82) [in black case].